Hi. It's Mike with UGtastic. I'm here at GOTO Conference 2015 and I'm standing here with Jay Fields, who gave a talk on unselfish testing. Thank you very much for taking the time to speak with me. So unselfish testing, what does that mean and where did it come from? Sure.
So I used to be a consultant with ThoughtWorks. I was there for several years and worked with a lot of clients and a lot of people that were a lot smarter than me, much more senior than me, learned a lot from them, and then worked with a lot of junior people just coming out of college. And I noticed that people spent a lot of time testing, not necessarily always very effectively. And so I just looked for patterns that I thought would make people more effective. And those turned into blog posts, which eventually turned into a book, which eventually turned into presenting today.
But unselfish, what does that mean? Sure.
It's thinking about the team. Whenever say you practice TDD, and so your workflow is you sit down and you write a failing test, and then you fix the test, maybe you refactor, but you ever notice the emphasis is always on refactoring of the code. Nobody ever says, "Well, okay, spend some time on the test . " And so you're being selfish at that point. If you're only working on writing code for the feature that you're currently working on, you're really only thinking about yourself. You're thinking about delivering that individual feature. So unselfish testing is about creating tests that are more maintainable for the entire team. So I may write this test and I may quit, and six months down the road, you're tasked with fixing a test because the domain has changed or something's changed. And now you have a broken test that I wrote for my purposes that I didn't really think about you. I was selfish. So you have a test that you have to spend more time debugging. So in my presentation, I actually show a really kind of a selfish test, and it takes you 10 minutes, 10 steps, it's really 10 minutes and 10 steps just to get to the expected value of the test.
Yeah.
It's so funny that that's so appropriate. Because I hadn't really articulated that. I look at open source projects, and one of the first things I do when I'm trying to understand what they're doing is go look at the test, and I was just feeling the pain looking at a library yesterday, saying, "What is the call?
How do I call the certain method in their little DSL?
" But when I looked at it, they actually had YAML that was loaded, and then they did some reflection on their own API, which caused the tests to execute and validate that it worked, which is great. But they didn't tell me anything about how or why it worked . Now I'm trying to parse whether I'm dealing with their DSL or I'm dealing with a DSL that's in the test framework. And that's not an RSpec thing, that's just their metapro gramming around generating a bunch of data.
Sure.
Yeah, that's a common problem is you write a test, and you think, "Okay, well, I have a lot of different ideas.
How do I abstract some of this out and kind of put it in a common place?
" And if you have an idea that kind of flows throughout your entire test suite, then it's great to abstract. Because you coming in, you look at the first test, and you 're kind of lost, and then you find the abstractions, but those are valuable across the whole test suite, and that's good. But if you come in, and there's a grouping of tests, just a couple different tests, and they have to connect to read some YAML or go through some specific DSL, and then you spend all of this time reading, just trying to figure out the test, and that doesn't even help you with the underlying open source library. You're just trying to understand this test, and the person who wrote it, they probably wrote something that's very sophisticated and not too hard to work with. Mm-hmm. If you know what you're doing. Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Right?
But when you come to it fresh...
Yeah.
It's a different world.
Especially, like, this was a DSL that I was... or they had a DSL for the configuration, so it's already there. There's that overhead of trying to just figure out how they 're doing the DSL.
Right.
Much less which method do I call to register XYZ with the framework, and it's like, "Oh, man. " Meanwhile, you just want to learn the framework.
You don't want to learn how clever they were in their tests .
Yeah.
And that's really the problem with a lot of the stuff you see out there, is people are very clever in their tests. Mm-hmm. But they don't realize that that cleverness does not help future maintainers, until you internalize it, but you're forcing someone to internalize it.
Right. Right?
They have no choice but to internalize all of that compl ication. Yeah, and if they're just coming to an API, and they've got a task to do, and they're trying to just say, "Oh, how can I use this thing to do my task," then they have to spend hours just to figure out, "Oh, no, it's not going to work. " Yeah.
You know?
And I don't think anyone's doing it maliciously.
Yeah.
It's just, like, before, we didn't even write tests. Mm-hmm. And then we all kind of dove in to just writing tests all the time, and nobody took a step back.
And not enough people, in my opinion, took a step back and said, "Why are we writing this test? You know, did it help us write the code? Well, that's a different test, maybe, than did it help us maintain the code?
" And maybe even that is different than documentation or having someone come fresh to a framework and try to understand it. They're different tests. And it sounds like the kind of problem that Gherkin and Cuc umber were trying to solve in a way where they were shooting at using these descriptive steps to say, like, "This is what it's supposed to do. " I mean, of course, there was some complexity. I mean, in the background to actually do the thing, but, I mean, do you touch on that at all in your talk, how some frameworks seem to be trying to make things a little bit more human on the surface, at least? Or is that... I didn't really touch on it. I mean, but I have opinions on it, obviously. You know, I think teams should basically just work with what makes them successful. But I don't think anybody should adopt that stuff thinking it's the silver bullet. Or... No. I don't think anybody should adopt that. I'm saying, "Okay, we're gonna make this so that it's human readable first and then machine implement. " I think it'll vary by team. Some teams will benefit from that and maybe they'll use it for documentation. There are teams that have a lot of success with kind of BDD -style stuff, but it's not for everyone. There are also people who want just concise, no-nonsense, maintainable tests, don't care about generating documentation, don't care about using the tests for customer collaboration. And that's what it comes down to. You have to...
What's your motivator? Right. What's the point of the Gherkin test if only programmers are ever gonna look at it? Right. Is it really helpful?
Because programmers know Ruby better than they know reading regexes of strings turned into Ruby.
Yeah. Yeah.
And also, just kind of going a little further, thinking about, as you were talking about having these really creative tests and maybe refactor to the hilt, I mean, is maybe DRY not necessarily the best thing when you're inside of a test ?
Yeah.
I mean, that's definitely strong in my talk. It really depends on the team. But I would say the larger the team, the less DRY or being dry is the appropriate choice. Because the larger the team, the more likely you are to run into a test that you've never seen before. Well, I guess it makes sense what context we're talking about. Within an individual test, obviously, you don't wanna repeat ideas.
Right.
And within an entire test suite, say, some type of factory that creates all of your test instances, that creates a test instance with default values .
Very helpful, obviously. And used throughout everywhere. So, DRY that up and reuse it everywhere. It's one concept. Reused everywhere. That's great.
Right.
But when you say, "Well, this group of tests in this file is one thing, and this is another thing, and this is another thing, and for this group, these parts of setup are applied, and for this group, these parts of setup are applied," but that's not really true. Setup is always applied everywhere.
And so, you have that conceptual overhead, and then any helper methods you have, there's more overhead, and I don't... If you're the person that wrote it, and you're the only person that ever maintains the code, then that's probably fine. Dry it out however you want, because it's gonna be your mental model, and just go with it.
Right.
No criticisms there. But if you work on, say, a 10-person team, and you start drying things out, and hiding a little complexity over here, and hiding a little complexity over here, you're not really reducing complexity. You're just hiding it in different places. And so now, when that test is broken, you're forcing me not only to understand that complexity, but I have to go find it as well.
So, I find that frustrating and selfish. So, what would be something that... As somebody who's sitting down and looking at implementing a test suite around a new product, what are maybe some rules of thumb that they might want to have in mind as they're kind of contemplating writing their test suite? First thing is just know your motivators. Know what's really important to you.
Do you want to do TDD?
Okay, well, that means you should, I don't know, write a test for everything, but just start there. Okay, so now I have a motivator that's gonna cause me to write a test for everything.
Great. What is code coverage?
I'm not really a fan of 100% code coverage, but some people are. That's gonna be a motivator for some of your tests. If you're not 100% code coverage, then you probably don't need to, say, test the methods of a framework that you're using.
Right. They're probably already tested, right?
So, know your motivators. I mean, the motivator of customer acceptance is another common one. Your manager told you to is another common one. There are a lot of reasons that people write tests, so the first thing, just know what direction your motivators are even putting you in. So, let's say that you only care about TDD for design, and another way that I like to look at my tests is RR. R-O-I, return on investment, and so, say, you only care about TDD, and you only care about ROI. So, cool. TDD everything. Get the benefits of TDD and get your improved design, you know, everything that everybody's been talking about with TDD. Do that. But just 'cause you wrote a test doesn't mean that it has to stay there.
Right. Right?
It doesn't need to live there. Instead, I look at my tests, I prefer to look at my tests through ROI, and so every test has an ROI, negative or positive. And so, say you write a test, say you're an insurance company, and you need to look your customers up. Buy social security number. So, social needs to be correct, so you have a validation on social, but you don't need to get correct that they have no integers in their name, because there's no business value in keeping integers out of a name other than maybe, you know, one in a hundred, one in a million. You get a customer who's annoyed 'cause you put an integer in there, but they're not gonna cancel their insurance 'cause you put an integer in their name, right?
Right.
So, you don't necessarily need a test for that, but maybe you still TDD the feature, verifying that there's no integers in the name, you TDD it, and you get the good design benefits, delete the test, because if that gets broken, if there is a regression, it's minimal impact to the business.
Yeah.
Actually, you brought up the next question I was gonna ask about culling tests, and that a lot of teams I've seen will take a test and treat it like it's a sync or synced thing that can never be, like, once it's implemented, you can't touch it, and just sometimes I look at tests and I'm like, "Why are we even testing this? It doesn't matter. " Yeah. And people are afraid to delete it, because they don't know why they're testing it, and why does it matter?
And I don't know what my motivation for testing is. Maybe I can't delete that, because it's 100% code coverage, or, you know, my manager said this area needs to be 100% or something like that, but most of the time that's not the case. Most of the time it's just like, "Well, this is a test, so I can't possibly delete it," because, you know, imagine what would go wrong if somebody found out I deleted it.
Yeah.
But if you think about it, you know, really, if I deleted a test that was stopping a regression, and we had that regression, and it had almost no or no impact to the business, then it's really not a big deal, right?
Right.
So you mentioned that you have authored a book.
What's your book title?
"Working Effectively with Unit Tests. " "Working Effectively with Unit Tests. " Yeah.
And is that a Java-centric book, or is it general purpose?
I would say it's general purpose, but it's Java examples, which I know it's hard for some people to swallow. I personally love dynamic languages, but I wanted to make it accessible to the most people, so Java seemed like the good default choice.
Okay.
So it was "Working Effectively with Unit Tests. " "Working Effectively with Unit Tests. " "Working Effectively with Unit Tests. " It's on LeanPub, so DRM-free.
All the good programmer stuff. All right, great.
Well, thank you very much for taking the time to speak with me. Appreciate it. Thanks a lot. Yep.